International Union of Physiological Sciences Records 1889-1989 Mss.610.6.In82
American Philosophical Society
International Union of Physiological Sciences Records
1889-1989
Mss.610.6.In82
American Philosophical Society
27.0 Linear feet
To promote the science of physiology and the exchange of ideas, the first congress of the International Union of Physiological Sciences (IUPS) was held in Basle, Switzerland, in 1889, and congresses have been held every three years since. The Union was incorporated at Washington, D.C., in 1953. The bulk of the Records of the IUPS relate to the International Congresses. Although representation is uneven, with a gap between 1907-1920, the records include programs, lists of members, abstracts of communications, and photographs, with more substantial documentation for meetings held in the United States. The collection also includes some general correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports of the Secretary, Executive Committee and Council correspondence, records relating to budgets, record books, and photographs.
International Union of Physiological Sciences. Congress
Scope and Contents note
The collection is organized in the following series:
I. Congresses
II. Adhering Societies/Union International Unions
III. Executive/Council
IV. Committees and Commissions
V. Photographs
A. Congress Photographs
B. Other Photographs
VI. History
A. Constitution, By-Laws
VII. Ephemera
VIII. Bound Correspondence and Materials
General note
Table of contents available.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the IUPS, initially through Wallace Fenn, John Hubbard and Maurice Visscher, 1969-1980.
Biographical/Historical note
The International Union of Physiological Sciences (IUPS) was incorporated in 1953 at Washington, D.C., formalizing an earlier practice of persons in or interested in Physiological Science organizing international congresses around the core of Physiological Science. The purpose was to exchange, promote and further the knowledge of Physiological Science throughout the world. The first congress was held in 1889.
Membership is extended, not to individual scientists, but to national societies, unions, committees, academies or organizations from around the world. The members, called Adhering Societies, have a direct or sometimes related interest in Physiological Science.
The International Union of Physiological Sciences is not a professional association in the usual sense, organizing professional meetings from time to time. Rather, the meetings, or as they are called "Congresses", are the International Union of Physiological Sciences.
The organizing arrangement considers the incorporation of the IUPS the institutionalization of an earlier procedure for establishing and calling Congresses through a body of persons called "The Permanent Committee." This apparently evolved into the present functions of the "Executive Committee and the "Council." One or both of these bodies may establish, from time to time, an organizing committee for a particular congress. This was obviously done in the case of the XXIV Congress held in Washington, D.C.
Minutes; Photoprints; Physiology--Societies, etc
- Series I - Congresses
  General note
  Container List
  Scope and Contents note
  The documents in this series represent the Congresses somewhat unevenly. The XXIV Congress held in Washington, D.C. in 1968 is most comprehensively documented. The files of the earlier Congresses are less complete.
  By the nature of the IUPS it is obvious that some correspondence in the Congresses Series and some in the Executive/Council Series could be interchangeable. In some instances a letter was found to be in both files. Rather than solve an organizational imponderable, the rationale of the files' organization was to accept what had been received as Congresses correspondence, as a Congress document, even though it could also have been an Executive/Council document.
  Otherwise the Congresses files, expand or not, as the existing material may or may not permit division into various subdivisions, such as:
  Correspondence
  Announcements
  Proceedings
  Opening Statements
  Etc.
  - I Congress 1889 Basle (Box 1)
  - II Congress 1892 Luttich (Liege)
  - III Congress 1895 Bern
  - IV Congress 1898 Cambridge
  - V Congress 1901 Turin
  - [There is no archival material from the VI Congress in this collection.]
  - VII Congress 1907 Heidelberg
  - [There is no archival material from the VIII Congress in this collection.]
  - IX Congress 1913 Groningen, 3 folders
  - X Congress 1920 Paris
  - XI Congress 1923 Edinburgh
  - XII Congress 1926 Stockholm
  - XIII Congress 1929 Boston, 4 folders
  - XIV Congress 1932 Rome, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - XIV Congress 1932 Rome (Program & Communications)
  - XV Congress 1935 Leningrad-Moscow, 4 folders
  - XVI Congress 1938 Zurich, 7 folders
  - XVI Congress 1938 Zurich (Discussion & Themes - Demonstrations)
  - XVI Congress 1938 Zurich (History)
  - XVII Congress 1947 Oxford, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - XVII Congress 1947 Oxford (List of Members)
  - XVII Congress 1947 Oxford (History background correspondence)
  - XVII Congress 1947 Oxford (History)
  - XVIII Congress 1950 Copenhagen (List of members)
  - XVIII Congress 1950 Copenhagen, 3 folders
  - XVIII Congress 1950 Copenhagen (Abstracts Program)
  - XVIII Congress 1950 Copenhagen (Symposium Chemoreceptors & Chemoreceptive Reactions)
  - XVIII Congress 1950 Copenhagen (History)
  - XVIII Congress 1950 Copenhagen (Conditioned Reflexes and Reflex Theory, Bykou, K.M.)
  - XIX Congress 1953 Montreal (Directory of Members) (Box 4)
  - XIX Congress 1953 Montreal
  - XIX Congress 1953 Montreal (Program, Program Changes, Abstracts)
  - XIX Congress 1953 Montreal (General Information)
  - XIX Congress 1953 Montreal (History)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (General Information)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (Program Tours and Excursions)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (Directory of Members)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (Report of the Secretary)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (3 abstracts) (Box 5)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (Reports in Russian & Program)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (2 Program - abstracts)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (3 Opening Plenary Session) (3 General Information) (Bulletin)
  - XX Congress 1956 Brussels (History)
  - XXI Congress 1959 Buenos Aires, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
  - XXI Congress 1959 Buenos Aires, 9 folders
  - XXI Congress 1959 Buenos Aires (Symposium Life in Space)
  - XXI Congress 1959 Buenos Aires (History)
  - XXII Congress 1962 Leiden (Correspondence), 1961 (Box 7)
  - XXII Congress 1962 Leiden (Correspondence)
  - XXII Congress 1962 Leiden (List of Members)
  - XXII Congress 1962 Leiden, 4 folders
  - XXII Congress 1962 Leiden (Information, Information Processing in the Nervous System, Proceedings)
  - XXII Congress 1962 Leiden (2 Proceedings)
  - XXII Congress 1962 Leiden (History)
  - XXIII Congress 1965 Tokyo, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - XXIII Congress 1965 Tokyo (List of Participants)
  - XXIII Congress 1965 Tokyo (Minutes)
  - XXIII Congress 1965 Tokyo (Book in Chinese Characters-Program)
  - XXIII Congress 1965 Tokyo (Proceedings, Abstracts)
  - XXIII Congress 1965 Tokyo (2 History)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence), Jan. 1968-August 1968 (Box 9)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence), May 1968-1969
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence), 1969
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence), 1970-1971
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Speakers-Papers-Symposia), 1966-1968 (Box 10)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Symposia correspondence), 1966-1968
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Alternate Speakers-Papers-Symposia), 1967-1968
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Invited Speakers-Recent Advances in Physiology)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Satellite Symposia)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Bound Correspondence), 1968-1969 (Box 11)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence: The Way of the Investigator by Cannon)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Program Schedule of Events, Preliminary Program for Affiliate Members)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Organizing Committee-Atlantic City)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Registrants)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Opening Speech)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Announcement)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (2 Proceedings, Program)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Special Lectures), 1967-1968
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Minutes-Attendance)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Fenn-IUPS History Volumes Surplus)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (History)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence), 1964 (Box 12)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence), 1965-1966
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Correspondence), 1967
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (Congress Chairmen Correspondence)
  - XXIV Congress 1968 Washington, D.C. (A Report and an Evaluation of the Role of Such Congresses: Visscher and Wulff)
  - XXV Congress 1971 Munich (Agenda) (Box 13)
  - XXV Congress, 1971; 4 folders
  - XXV Congress (Satellite Symposia Correspondence), 1971
  - XXV Congress (Satellite Symposia), 1971
  - XXV Congress (Directory of Registrants), 1971
  - XXV Congress (General Information), 1971
  - XXV Congress (First Announcement), 1971
  - XXV Congress (Final Announcement), 1971
  - XXV Congress (Program), 1971
  - XXV Congress (Proceedings 2 Folders), 1971 (Box 14)
  - XXVI Congress 1974 New Delhi (Steering Committee)
  - XXVI Congress 1974 New Delhi
  - XXVI Congress 1974 New Delhi (Directory of Registrants)
  - XXVI Congress 1974 New Delhi (General Assembly Minutes)
  - XXVI Congress 1974 New Delhi (Minutes & Reports)
  - XXVI Congress (Proceedings), 1974
  - XXVII Congress 1977 Paris (Agenda, Minutes) (Box 15)
  - XXVII Congress 1977 Paris (Program)
  - XXVII Congress 1977 Paris
  - XXVII Congress 1977 Paris (Proceedings - Abstracts - Lectures - Roundtables)
  - XXVIII Congress 1978 Budapest (General Information - Scientific Program)
  - XXVIII Congress 1980 Budapest (General Assembly Minutes)
  - XXVIII Congress 1980 Budapest (Proceedings - Abstracts)
  - XXIX Congress 1983 Sydney (Box 16)
  - XXIX Congress 1983 Sydney (Program)
  - XXIX Congress 1983 Sydney (General Assembly Minutes)
  - XXIX Congress 1983 Sydney (Proceedings - Abstracts)
  - XXX Congress 1986 Vancouver
  - XXX Congress 1986 Vancouver (General Assembly Delegates)
  - XXX Congress 1986 Vancouver (Minutes General Assembly) (Box 17)
  - XXX Congress 1986 Vancouver (Program), 2 folders
  - XXX Congress 1986 Vancouver (Minutes - General Assembly)
  - XXX Congress 1986 Vancouver (Proceedings)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (Agenda)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (Final Announcement)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (General Assembly Delegates)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (Minutes General Assembly)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (Program)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (Satellite Meeting, Training Course, Teaching Physiology in Developing Countries)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (Proceedings, Abstracts)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (Definitions of the Aims & Activities of IUPS Commissions - Interim Guidelines)
  - XXXI Congress 1989 Helsinki (Abstracts) (Box 18)
  - XXXII Congress 1993 Glasgow
  - XXXII Congress 1993 Glasgow (Agenda - General Assembly)
  - XXXII Congress 1993 Glasgow (Minutes - General Assembly)
  - XXXII Congress 1993 Glasgow (Abstracts), 2 folders
  - XXXII Congress 1993 Glasgow (Commission Reports to the General Assembly)
  - XXXII Congress 1993 Glasgow (Abstracts) (Box 19)
  - XXXII Congress 1993 Glasgow (Program)
  - XXXII Congress 1993 Glasgow (The Logic of Life, Boyd & Noble)
  - XXXIII Congress 1997 St. Petersburg (Memorandum Members - General Assembly)
  - XXXIII Congress 1997 St. Petersburg (Agenda - General Assembly Minutes)
  - XXXIII Congress 1997 St. Petersburg (Report to the General Assembly - Committee on Ethical Aspects of Physiological Sciences)
  - XXXIII Congress 1997 St. Petersburg (Letter or Note), n.d.
  - XXXIV Congress, 2001
- Series II - Adhering Societies/Union International Unions
  Initially, this series contains material about member organizations, such as correspondence, activities and background information. However, it is not limited to members, but includes "supporting societies" and any organization or body that has a declared interest in the work of the congresses. In some instances those bodies are themselves other scientific unions. Material pertaining to IUPS Regional Meetings and/or Symposia that appear to be inspired by the activities of the Adhering Society or Supporting Society and are not clearly a part of a congress are also organized in this series.
  Those symposia or satellite meetings or even regional meetings that appear to be clearly a part of a congress are filed together with that congress.
  The United States is represented in the Adhering Societies/Union International Unions series under the heading: U.S. Committee. In fact, the U.S. Committee appears to be a function of the National Academy of Sciences, which technically would be the Adhering Society. The National Academy of Sciences, however, appears to have considerable expanse in its interests. Therefore, in order to collect the substantive aspect of the participation as a member of the IUPS, there is simply a file section titled "U.S. Committee" in this series.
  - African Association of Physiological Sciences (Box 20)
  - American Heart Association/Renal Section (Third International Congress of Nephrology)
  - American Physiological Society
  - American Physiological Society (XVI International Congress of Zoology)
  - Asian and Oceanic Physiological Societies
  - Association Latino Americana de Cencias Fisiologicas (ALSACF)
  - Australian Academy of Science (National Committee for Physiological Sciences)
  - Australian Academy of Science (Regional Meeting-Australia), 1972
  - Australian Academy of Science (Regional Meeting-Sydney), 1972
  - Belgium Society of Physiology and Pharmacology
  - Bulgarian Academy of Sciences (International Symposium on Motor Control), 1972
  - British Pharmacology Society (See: The Royal Society)
  - Canadian National Committee (Pacific Regional Meeting)
  - The Canadian Physiological Society
  - China Peking
  - China Taiwan
  - Czechoslovakia
  - Association of the Czechoslovak Medical Societies Czechoslovak Physiological Society-Regional Meeting Prague IUPS, 1991
  - Czechoslovakia Academy of Sciences (Institute of Physiology)
  - Deutsche Physiologische Gesellschaft E. V.
  - Deutsche Physiologische Gesellschaft E. V. (West Germany)
  - Dutch Society for Physiology and Pharmacology - The Netherlands
  - European Society for Clinical Respiratory Physiology - International Symposium on Chemical Regulation of Ventilation and its Related Disorders-Turkey, 1972
  - European Oocyte Club
  - European Society for Clinical Respiratory Physiology International Symposium on Chemical Relation of Ventilation and its related disorders - Turkey, 1972
  - Federation of European Physiological Societies (FEPS)
  - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology
  - Finland
  - [France] Association des Physilogistes, 1977
  - France Symposium International de Thermoregulation Comportementale, Lyon, 1970
  - Gesellschaft der Physiologen-East Germany
  - Hungary - Hungarian Physiological Society
  - India
  - India (Second Congress of Asian & Oceanian Physiological Societies), 1990
  - Indonesia
  - International Astronomical Union
  - International Brain Research Organization (IBRO) (Box 21)
  - International Council for Laboratory Animal Science
  - International Council of Scientific Unions, 1964-1969
  - International Council of Scientific Unions, 1970-1974
  - International Council of Scientific Unions, 1975-1991
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Meeting Vienna General Assembly), 1963-
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Meeting-Paris), 1968
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Meeting-Washington, D.C. General Assembly), 1968-
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Meeting-Madrid General Asembly), 1970-
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Codata Bulletin) (Box 22)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Committee on Scientific Teaching)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (International Biological Programme)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (International Biological Programme-Symposium on Man-made Changes in the Environment)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Scientific Committee on Antarctic Research)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Scientific Committee for International Biological Programs (SCRIBP))
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Special Committee on Problems of the Environment (SCOPE))
  - International Council of Scientific Unions (Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research (SCOR), 2 folders (Box 23)
  - International Foundation for Scientific & Technical Development (IFSTD)
  - International Society of Endocrinology
  - International Society for General Semantics
  - International Union of Biochemistry
  - International Union of Biochemists (Oxygen Symposium), 1963
  - International Union of Biochemists (Sixth International Congress of Biochemistry)
  - International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics
  - International Union for Immunology
  - International Union for Pharmacology
  - International Union for Pure and Applied Biophysics
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry]
  - International Union of Pharmacology (IUPHAR), 2 folders (Box 24)
  - International Union Pure and Applied Physics
  - International Scientific and Radio Union
  - IUPS Representatives to ICUS Unions, Scientific Associates and Special Committees
  - International Society for Pathophysiology
  - Israel
  - Israel Physiological and Pharmacological Society (Regional Meeting), 1984
  - Latin American Association of Physiological Sciences
  - Latin American Association of Physiological Sciences (Conference VI Chile), 1964
  - Latin American Association of Physiological Sciences (Conference VII Congress Argentina, 1966; 2 folders
  - Latin American Association of Physiological Sciences (IX Congress Brazil), 1969
  - Latin American Association of Physiological Sciences XVI Congress
  - [Latin American] Symposium, Buenos Aires Argentina, May 17-18, 1994
  - [Latin American] Symposium on Physiology of Reactive Oxygen Species, Argentina, March 17 - 19, 1992; May 15, 1993
  - Lebanon
  - Malaysian Society of Pharmacology
  - Membership List (Personnel Directory IUPS) (Box 25)
  - Pakistan (India)
  - Pan American Union
  - Poland
  - Regional IUPS Congress, n.d.
  - Romania
  - Romania - The Academy of the Socialist Republic of Romania (Regional Congress), 1970
  - Romania - Regional Conference of International Union of Physiological Sciences (Brasov 1970 Abstracts)
  - Romania - Regional Congress of the International Union of Physiological Sciences (Brasov 1970 Programs)
  - The Royal Society (Physiologists of the United Kingdom)
  - Section on Pharmacology (SEPHAR) (International Union of Physiological Sciences By-Laws, 1961 (Box 26)
  - Section on Pharmacology (SEPHAR) International Union of Physiological Sciences Correspondence
  - Section on Pharmacology (SEPHAR) 1961 International Union of Physiological Sciences (First Meeting Stockholm)
  - Section on Pharmacology (SEPHAR) (2nd meeting Prague), 1963
  - Society for Experimental Biology (Symposium Wales), 1971
  - The Society of Physiologist in Thailand
  - South Africa
  - South American Lecture Tours (Reports - Impressions - Statements) Correspondence
  - South American Lecture Tours (Reports-Impressions-Statement-Recollections)
  - Special Members, n.d.
  - Swiss Physiological Society
  - Technology Transfer Society
  - Turkey
  - United Arab Republic
  - UNESCO India Symposium (Environmental Physiology and Physiology in Arid Conditions), 1962
  - UNESCO, 1956, 1961-1966
  - UNESCO, 1969-1971
  - UNESCO Natural Sciences (Box 27)
  - UNESCO Council for International Organizations of Medical Sciences (CIOMS)
  - UNESCO International Cell Research Organization (ICRO)
  - U. S. National Committee Correspondence, 1958-59
  - U. S. National Committee Correspondence, 1961
  - U. S. National Committee Correspondence, 1962-67
  - U. S. National Committee Correspondence, 1968-1971
  - U. S. National Committee Correspondence, 1974
  - U. S. National Committee Correspondence, 1991
  - U. S. National Committee Correspondence, 1958-1965
  - U. S. National Committee Minutes, 1970-1977 (Box 28)
  - U. S. National Committee Minutes, 1991
  - U. S. National Committee Agenda
  - U. S. National Committee Constitution
  - U. S. S. R. Institute of Physiology (Georgian Academy of Sciences)
  - Venezuela
  - World Directory of Physiologists, 1977
  - World Directory of Physiologists, 1980
  - World Directory of Physiologists, 1991
  - World Health Organization
  - World Meteorological Society
- Series III - Executive/Council
  Based on earlier statements about the "Permanent Committee," this series begins with the files of the "Permanent Committee."
  Unfortunately, most of the material in the Executive/Council Series has been signed without the title of the author. It is apparent, in the case of some individuals, that they held more than one office at various times. Without an inscribed title under their name, their office at the time of writing is not necessarily known. Therefore, this series is mostly a chronological correspondence file.
  There did emerge from this material certain documents that were easily categorized. They are:
  Agenda
  Ballots
  Minutes (Includes Activities Reports)
  Treasurer's Reports and Accounts (Includes Auditor's Reports)
  Archivist's files and a publication called "Newsletter" material are also filed under their separate identities in the Executive/Council series. These were included because their functions appear to be the responsibility of the Executive/Council whether or not the offices of the Archivist and Editor of the Newsletter were in themselves necessarily Executive Committee or Council positions.
  The Executive/Council series does not include the correspondence of the officers of a particular congress, since each congress has its own officers named for that Congress only.
  - Permanent Committee Correspondence, 1935-1953; 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Permanent Committee Minutes, 1935-1953
  - Correspondence, 1950-1955; 2 folders
  - Correspondence, 1959-1991; 21 folders (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1965; 3 folders (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1969; 4 folders (Box 32)
  - Correspondence (Release of Prof. Samueloff), 1969-1970 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1997; 5 folders
  - Correspondence (Box 34)
  - Agenda
  - Minutes, 1953-1977; 3 folders
  - Minutes, 1979-1997; 4 folders (Box 35)
  - Minutes, n.d.
  - Archivist (Box 36)
  - Ballots
  - [Ballots] Proposed Slate, 1997-2001
  - Budget, 1992-1994
  - IUPS Council, 1989-1993
  - Treasurer Reports and Accounts, 1956-1989; 9 folders
  - Treasurer Audit Reports, 1979-1992 (Box 37)
  - Treasurer Audit Reports, 1994-1995
  - Treasurer - Reports-Accounts-Bank Statements-Insurance
  - Treasurer - Misc. Receipts, Notes, Letters, 1959-1965
  - [Treasurer] I.U.P.S. World Directory of Physiologists
  - Newsletter, 1960-1992; 3 folders (Box 38)
  - Newsletter, n.d.
  - Newsletter [Issuances], 1966-1978; 2 folders
  - Newsletter [Issuance] Vol 7 No. 2
  - Newsletter (Publications)
  - Lecture - Fenn Lecture
  - Lecture (Tours), 1960-1965
- Series IV - Committees and Commissions